Kappa Beta Fraternity; Records ua800.012
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Kappa Beta Fraternity Records
1937-2007
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Kappa Beta Fraternity (State University of New York at Albany)
ua800.012
1.5 cubic ft.
An artificial collection of memorabilia and paper records concerning the Kappa Beta Fraternity. Originally a Jewish fraternity, it became non-denominational in 1948.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Nahum Lewis 38, Rita Greenwald, Stephen Greenwald 40, Robert (Bob) Barron 52, Arnold Newman 56,57, Philip T. Coccia 66, Michael Bloom 67 and Michelle Miller.
Historical Note
The fraternity was created in the academic year 1936-37 to provide an atmosphere where Jewish students at the then New York State College for Teachers could socialize and enjoy Kosher meals. Kappa Beta was deactivated during WW II when most of its members were drafted or volunteered for the service. It was reestablished in 1946 and its newly elected president, Paul Wagner 48, pushed through an amendment to its constitution making KB non-sectarian. The fraternity continued to exist at the State University of New York at Albany until 1974 and alumni directories list one member as a graduate of the Class of 1980. Alumni of the fraternity held reunions until at least 2007.
Scope and Contents
An artificial collection of memorabilia and paper records including two histories of the fraternity (one by a founder, Nahum Lewis 38, and a second by Arnold Newman 56), drinking mugs, membership lists, newsletters, photographs, and reunion programs. Included in the records are photos, programs and memorabilia from reunions from 1946 through 2007.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged chronologically.
UAlbany Student Groups; Kappa Beta Fraternity (State University of New York at Albany)
- History of Kappa Beta Fraternity, by Nahum Lewis, 2001 (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 1)
- Photographs, ca. 1940-1955 (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 2)
- Certificate of Invitation to membership in Kappa Beta of Saul Stephen Greenwald (Greenwald was a charter member), 1937 May (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 3)
- Kappa Beta Reunion, 1952 May (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 4)
- Kappa Beta Personal Data, 1952 August (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 5)
- Kappa Beta Personal Data, 1952 August (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 6)
- Kappa Beta Dinner and Dance, 1952 October (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 7)
- Kappa Beta Banquet Dinner, 1955 May (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 8)
- Kappa Beta Reunion, 1970 October (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 9)
- Kappa Beta Reunion, 1976 October (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 10)
- Kappa Beta Reunion, 1976 October (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 11)
- Kappa Beta Diamond Jubilee, 1977 June-August (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 12)
- Kappa Beta Correspondence with Alumni Association, 1977-1978 (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 13)
- Kappa Beta Correspondence with Alumni Association, 1982 June-July (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 14)
- Kappa Beta University Reunion Documents, 1981 September-1992 June (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 15)
- Kappa Beta Reunion, 1991 October (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 16)
- Kappa Beta Reunion, 1991 October (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 17)
- University at Albany Foundation Annual Report (With Kappa Beta donors to annual fund circled), 1995-1996 (Box 1 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 18)
- Kappa Beta Fraternity List, 1976 October (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 1)
- Kappa Beta Directory, 1960-1961 (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 2)
- Kappa Beta Newsletter, 1954 May-1956 June (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 3)
- Kappa Beta Memorial Fund, 1997 (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 4)
- Kappa Beta Reunion Newsletter, 1997 June (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 5)
- Kappa Beta Reunion Photographs, 2002 June (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 6)
- Kappa Beta 65th Anniversary Weekend Program, 2002 June (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 7)
- Kappa Beta Reunion list of Brothers 1938-1980, 2002 June (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 8)
- Kappa Beta Mardi Gras Ball Program, 1956 February (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 9)
- Kappa Beta Reunion Dinner Photograph, 1946 May (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 10)
- Kappa Beta Pledge Paddle (loose-not in box), Undated (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 11)
- Bnai Chaim, Brothers for Life: A Personal, Anecdotal History of Kappa Beta Fraternity, 1937-1974, by Arnold Newman, Undated (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 12)
- Kappa Beta Memorabilia, Undated (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 13)
- Kappa Beta 70th Reunion gift (white tile with Kappa Beta shield, motto, and 1937-2007 date), Undated (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 14)
- Kappa Beta Reunion cocktail napkin, 2002 (Box 2 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 15)
- Reunion files - Includes 1960-61 Kappa Beta Alumni Directory, annual Kappa Beta Newsletters, 1957-60, and the Initiation Certificate for Robert Barron, 52, 1962; 1992-2002 (Box 3 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 1)
- Photo album, 65th and 70th reunions, 2002; 2007 (Box 3 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 2)
- Kappa Beta Spring Weekend 65 Brown Jug, Undated (Box 4 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 1)
- Kappa Beta Beer Stein with "ARNIE, 1956", Undated (Box 4 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 2)
- Kappa Beta 20th Anniversary Beer Stein, 1957, Undated (Box 4 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 3)
- 60th Reunion cap, 1997 (Box 5 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 1)
- 65th Reunion cap, 2002 (Box 5 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 2)
- 65th Reunion cap, 2002 (Box 5 (Kappa Beta Fraternity Records), Folder 3)